<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Bubble + Sprout</title>
  
  <subtitle>A platform for positive expansion</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-03-21T15:02:44.676Z</updated>
  <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Karin Schrijvers</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Picnic Parenting</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/03/20/picnicparenting/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/03/20/picnicparenting/</id>
    <published>2019-03-20T15:03:03.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-03-21T15:02:44.676Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>In collaboration with <a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a></em></p><p>When the kids don’t want to brush their teeth before bed and we are tired and ready for me time, the easiest solution often seems to raise our voice and loose our cool. Or is it? </p><a id="more"></a>  <p>How about we first press our internal pause button and introduce some mindfulness into our interaction with the kids? It can really help us enjoy family time more by learning to respond to each other in a calmer more rational manner.</p><p>When I notice that my frustration or anger or any other such emotion is being stimulated, I use the following mindful practice that I have developed to help me stay present and defuse potentially explosive situations. It has shown me time and again that parenting can in fact be a picnic. But please remember this is a practice and thus takes some practising before it becomes a habit. Most specially when it’s time to brush teeth and we are tired and desperate for that elusive me time…</p><p>Here’s how I do it: First and foremost I press that <strong>pause</strong> button. Sometimes this means I have to actually leave the room. (Trust me, the kids will soon understand why you do this and that it is, in fact, a good thing.) I then lift the centre of my sternum and stand up straight in order to <strong>improve my posture</strong>. A better posture will better ground me and help me <strong>connect with my breath</strong>. It is only after reconnecting with my body and breath, that I consciously take <strong>notice of my thoughts</strong>. They usually appreciate a bit of attention as long as we don’t judge them or get lost in their drama. It is here that I <strong>infuse the moment with full awareness</strong> and accept what is unfolding without denying nor escalating the situation. Finally, after this moment of mindful awareness – because that is what this is called – you will find it so much easier to face the kids again and <strong>choose a mindful response</strong>. </p><p>If this all seems a bit much to remember, simply remind yourself of the six steps using the PICNIC acronym below: </p><p><strong>P</strong>ause<br><strong>I</strong>mprove your posture<br><strong>C</strong>onnect with your breath<br><strong>N</strong>otice your thoughts<br><strong>I</strong>nfuse the moment with awareness<br><strong>C</strong>hoose a mindful response</p><p>Remember, none of these steps have to take long at all. A tiny pause; a physical adjustment and deeper breath; a scan of your thoughts; your full awareness of the moment. Then see how this has set you up for a mindful response instead of a hasty reaction.</p><p>Every single time I use the PICNIC technique, I manage to stay composed in a challenging situation or relax into the imperfection of the moment. The kids very clearly understand that I am calming myself down so that I can respond in a much more rational manner. By modelling this practice to our children and letting them experience how it affects our response, we can cultivate mindfulness in them and eventually equip them with a priceless tool for life.</p><p><em><a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a> bring yoga and mindfulness to London families. They are currently preparing to raise funds for OM:POP - their Mindful Kids &amp; Families Pop-Up Events. Please click <a href="https://www.spacehive.com/om-pop-mindful-pop-up" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">here</span></a> to show your support.</em></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://hereforyouforthem.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:grey&quot;&gt;HERE for you for them&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the kids don’t want to brush their teeth before bed and we are tired and ready for me time, the easiest solution often seems to raise our voice and loose our cool. Or is it? &lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="motherhood" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/motherhood/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Slow Dance</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/03/07/slowdance/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/03/07/slowdance/</id>
    <published>2019-03-07T21:17:13.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-03-09T10:09:43.725Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To do or to be? That truly is a recurring question.<br>Do Be Do Be Do… Like a catchy Sinatra tune we cannot shake. Eternally on repeat on the turntable that is our mind.</p><a id="more"></a><p>So how did we get to dance into March already? I am still working on my New Year’s resolutions… Or at least so it seems. Does this mean I have not officially started doing enough? Or have I perhaps been doing so much that time has passed me by? </p><p>Mindful parenting, minimalism and teaching yoga constantly expose me to the friction of a wealth of contradictions. On the one hand, I find myself lecturing about the need to pause, to simplify and to observe. On the other hand, there is me attempting to welcome equanimity in the midst of the kids’ school programmes, my writing deadlines and teaching schedules. </p><p>But is this friction between doing and being such a bad thing? As far as I know –  and this covers pretty much the full extent of my Physics knowledge – friction transforms kinetic energy into thermal energy. And I also seem to remember that it slows down the two objects that move past each other. Exactly like the warming embrace in a slow dance between two strangers in the night. Do Be Do Be Do.</p><p>As long as both doing and being (the metaphorical dance partners in this show) contribute a balanced amount of effort, the dance should remain an elegant waltz around movement and slowing down. I am rather looking forward to slow dance the year away in the warm embrace of such a contradictory equilibrium. No need to feel bad. Not about not doing enough. Not about not pausing enough.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;To do or to be? That truly is a recurring question.&lt;br&gt;Do Be Do Be Do… Like a catchy Sinatra tune we cannot shake. Eternally on repeat on the turntable that is our mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="yoga" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/yoga/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Kindred Ritual</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/01/24/kindredritual/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/01/24/kindredritual/</id>
    <published>2019-01-24T12:48:36.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-01-24T15:12:52.521Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>In collaboration with <a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a></em></p><p>We live in a world that offers endless possibilities for us to compare ourselves to others. But do we as parents really help our children by modelling comparison as a coping strategy? </p><a id="more"></a><p>Before the insurgence of social media, parents’ exposure to fellow parents was limited to the school gate and family gatherings with established friends. Not that these two didn’t occasionally trigger stress hormones. But modern-day parents have the added luxury of 24-hour access to all the perfect parents across the world. How lucky are we!?!</p><p>As far as comparisons go, we seem to have two choices. Downward comparison is a method to help boost our sense of wellbeing by contrasting ourselves with those who are worse off. Who doesn’t remember their parents telling them about all the hungry children in the world who would be very happy with those vegetables? I, for one, recall how this guilt trigger added a rather bitter taste to my greens.</p><p>Upward comparison, on the other hand, is very popular in situations where we feel or are made to feel overwhelmed by others’ apparent strengths that we ourselves lack. Let’s again reach back to our childhood and evoke one of those moments where you were invited to wonder why other children weren’t behaving as badly as you. Remember how helpless this made you feel?</p><p>Psychologists would no doubt confirm that both types of comparison are human strategies that help us deal with threats, build resilience and establish identity. And yes, it does indeed make sense for us to establish where exactly we stand in various social environments. But what other, perhaps even better, technique could we employ instead of this often rather unkind variety?</p><p>We evidently do a lot of thinking about our life and about how it holds up in comparison to other people’s lives. Regrettably, a great deal of our thoughts appear to be critical. Rather than reacting to a situation with the flawed strategy of comparison, it makes sense for us to assimilate and model to our children a response that is kind to both our self and others. This is where the mindful practice of gratitude could help. Gratitude feeds contentment because it is sourced from within and does not need others as a benchmark.</p><p>So how can we introduce ourselves and our children to this kinder alternative coping mechanism? Through trial and error, our family has come up with an – almost – daily gratitude ritual that works both for us and our 8- and 6-year-old. While enjoying our evening meal, each family member gets to share one thing they are the least grateful for and three things they are the most grateful for. The setup is pretty informal, but the one strict rule is that nobody is allowed to interrupt or comment, unless advice is asked for. </p><p>We have consciously included the one ‘sorrow’ because we feel it is important for our children to know that in order to be content and blossom you do not have to be happy all the time. An unexpected bonus of this inclusion of sorrows is that it provides a platform where uncomfortable subjects can be brought up.</p><p>In our experience, the family gratitude ritual we have landed on offers the perfect moment to cherish the positives in our own personal lives, without the need for comparison. An opportunity to bring grace to sorrows and occasionally even learn from them. A beautiful evening ritual to revel in unbiased support for negative things and communal joy for positive things.</p><p><em>With many thanks to Dana Dyskterhuis and Jen Armstrong for giving me the opportunity to post my musings on their platform. It has been a real privilege to get to know these two elegantly powerful ladies at <a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a> and to be playing an ongoing part in OM:POP - their Mindful Kids &amp; Families Pop-Up Events.</em></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://hereforyouforthem.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:grey&quot;&gt;HERE for you for them&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in a world that offers endless possibilities for us to compare ourselves to others. But do we as parents really help our children by modelling comparison as a coping strategy? &lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="motherhood" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/motherhood/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Cuppa Comfort</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/01/17/cuppacomfort/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/01/17/cuppacomfort/</id>
    <published>2019-01-17T21:17:13.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-03-08T19:43:31.617Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A cup of Sencha tea is projecting swirly steam patterns in the low winter sunshine on my desk while I settle down on my sheepskin covered stool. There is something very homely and grounding about brewing a hot drink before a new beginning.</p><a id="more"></a><p>And it doesn’t even stop at beginnings. I will also gravitate towards our stove-top kettle whenever I feel the need to take myself away from a situation, a thinking pattern or an activity. A cuppa to mark an ending or at least a break.</p><p>My husband is surprised by the amount of tea I manage to drink in a day, and equally by the number of half-empty tea cups he finds around our home. So I thought I would try and find out why exactly I brew so much tea (green or herbal depending on the time of day), by drawing up a list of circumstances in which I find myself drawn to the kettle on our hob:</p><ul><li>First thing upon waking</li><li>Before I sit down to write </li><li>As a planned pause</li><li>To think things over</li><li>At a writing impasse</li><li>After lunch with a square of dark chocolate</li><li>Walking in from the cold after running errands</li><li>When a friend visits for a chat</li><li>Before I plan my yoga classes</li><li>After school pickup to share a pot with the kids</li><li>When the kids are safely tucked in bed and I’ve kissed them goodnight</li><li>…</li></ul><p>The list is by no means exhaustive, but it does show that in its essence my personal tea ceremony is not so much about the tea as about the occasion. Waiting for the water to boil. Opening the scented tea caddie. Spooning loose petals or flowers in the strainer. Pouring freshly boiled water in the mug or pot. Allowing the tea enough time to work its magic.</p><p>They are all ceremonial acts in an occasion to remove myself from the fast pace of life. Each cup that I brew throughout the day represents a punctuation mark that offers me a mindful pause in which to focus on the moment and come home within myself.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;A cup of Sencha tea is projecting swirly steam patterns in the low winter sunshine on my desk while I settle down on my sheepskin covered stool. There is something very homely and grounding about brewing a hot drink before a new beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="yoga" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/yoga/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Choose Love</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2018/12/17/choose-love/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2018/12/17/choose-love/</id>
    <published>2018-12-17T14:55:23.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-12-17T20:17:39.134Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yes! We have finally said goodbye to the four builders who spent the past nine weeks refurbishing our small London home. While most of our belongings were safely tucked away in a dust-free storage cube down the road, we were to waltz around settling clouds of dust before bedding down for the night.</p><a id="more"></a><p>At 7.30, like clockwork, the four men would arrive on our patio. We had to time our kitchen sink wash just right to avoid making a spectacle of ourselves in front of the four-men crowd. Sometimes there were five or even six, if the job of the day required extra hands. When it came to leaving at the end of the day, they were a little less punctual. But usually we would have the building site back to ourselves from around 4.30 in the afternoon.</p><p>Normally, whenever I am not teaching or presenting away from home, I tend to return to write, study, practise and spend time with the kids after school. I love the simplicity and warmth of being at home. It is the place that makes me feel safe, that fosters my physical and mental wellbeing. It is where I practise yoga, which grounds me. It is where I meditate, which allows me to grow. So where was I to find home when the physical space that represented my habitual home, was constantly invaded by strangers and loud noises? </p><p>During the past nine weeks, a large chunk of my non-teaching time was spent in comfortable coffee shops with fashionable hot drinks. I would go for a swim followed by a sauna and a proper wash at the gym. There was my friend’s cozy place to which she had given me the key so I could make myself at home during the day. Or I would simply choose to wander through the London streets and discover new places. How lucky was I? Yet this lack of a familiar home still managed to cause me some degree of stress.</p><p>On one such ‘forced’ London wandering, I happened across the Choose Love shop in Soho and was drawn in by their tag line: “Imagine a world where you can shop your heart out, leave with nothing and feel great about it.” A mindful minimalist’s dream! Choose Love (<a href="https://choose.love/" target="_blank" rel="external">https://choose.love/</a>) turned out to be a pop-up shop with gifts that could make a real difference to someone’s life.</p><p>There are approximately 65 million people in the world today who are literally forced to leave their home, and this without the prospect of ever returning. These are people who have been driven out of their home and country due to persecution, war or violence. Their leaving was not a choice. Nor do they have access to warm coffee shops, hot showers or their friends’ cozy homes. Imagine the degrees of stress they must be experiencing. It simply makes sense to buy gifts that don’t come home with us but are sent directly to the uprooted refugees who truly need them. What’s not to love about that?</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Yes! We have finally said goodbye to the four builders who spent the past nine weeks refurbishing our small London home. While most of our belongings were safely tucked away in a dust-free storage cube down the road, we were to waltz around settling clouds of dust before bedding down for the night.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="minimalism" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/minimalism/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Elegant Strength</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2018/09/11/elegant-strength/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2018/09/11/elegant-strength/</id>
    <published>2018-09-11T21:30:37.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-09-12T13:22:04.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am a daughter, a sister, a wife, a mother… I am a woman.<br>And this feels like the season to celebrate all of our distinctly feminine qualities. It is time for our daughters and our sons to be inspired by and proud of their own inherently feminine strengths. </p><a id="more"></a><p>As a mother, I still often overhear ‘responsible’ parents address their children with such cringeworthy statements as: “Oh, why don’t you just man up?” or “Stop crying like a girl.” First of all, what is wrong with a good old cry? After all, it will release toxins, reduce stress and reset our mind. Secondly – and obviously more to the point within the context of this post – do we even realise what we are saying here? Acting ‘like a man’ makes you stronger? Crying ‘like a girl’ shows weakness? Surely we should know better by now?</p><p>And now feels like exactly the right time to consider what true strength actually means to us. Let’s start rooting for an attitude that includes such qualities as elegance, compassion, intuition and even imperfection. Our current society already has more than its fair share of bullying masculinity on display. Can we honestly continue to make our children believe that strength is purely expressed by flexing excessively developed muscles? Can we seriously condone intimidation and force as the ultimate methods to make a difference?</p><p>Here’s to a whole new way of showing strength, starting with the shameless promotion of femininity.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;I am a daughter, a sister, a wife, a mother… I am a woman.&lt;br&gt;And this feels like the season to celebrate all of our distinctly feminine qualities. It is time for our daughters and our sons to be inspired by and proud of their own inherently feminine strengths. &lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="motherhood" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/motherhood/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Humble Leadership</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2018/05/22/humble-leadership/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2018/05/22/humble-leadership/</id>
    <published>2018-05-22T21:24:36.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-05-22T22:06:18.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>“Movement follows breath.” A classic yoga teacher statement. But does it express what is happening on the yoga mat for most of us? What part does the mind play in this setup? Does it simply withdraw and watch the intuitive breath lead the body’s movement? Or does it constantly try to control the breath and command the body?</p><a id="more"></a><p>If we were to bravely draw a comparison between the yogic observation above and a family’s dynamics, our family unit would be the moving body, our kids the intuitive breath and we, their parents, the ever so rational and controlling mind… Do I simply sit back and watch the kids define our family’s rhythm? Or do I relentlessly tell them what to do to try and make our household run ‘smoothly’? </p><p>Apparently I have occasionally been subscribing to the philosophy of Servant Leadership. Little did I know that there is, in fact, an official title for my attempt at leading the kids by following them. Unfortunately, most parents these days have a negative reaction to being called their kids’ servant. So how about, in this context, we call it Humble Leadership?</p><p>A humble leader is someone who aims to empower their followers. It is amazing how well a humble approach is received by our children. When they feel empowered to lead the way, they will also happily follow. When they feel empowered to express their opinions, they will also respect ours. When they feel empowered to try something new, they will learn from the mistakes they may experience.</p><p>Scientists are becoming increasingly aware of the strong correlation between our breath’s rhythm and our mental well-being. So if we were to expand on our analogy, it would make sense to learn to follow our kids’ rhythm a little more often and let intuition lead reasoning.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;“Movement follows breath.” A classic yoga teacher statement. But does it express what is happening on the yoga mat for most of us? What part does the mind play in this setup? Does it simply withdraw and watch the intuitive breath lead the body’s movement? Or does it constantly try to control the breath and command the body?&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="motherhood" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/motherhood/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Old Fashioned</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2018/04/16/oldfashioned/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2018/04/16/oldfashioned/</id>
    <published>2018-04-16T12:07:23.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-16T14:01:22.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My two late grandmothers were very skilful at making and mending clothes. My father’s mother was a natural at crocheting. Every summer, I still proudly wear one of her handmade cardigans. My mother’s mother was a meticulous sock darner and I remember her working her way through a basket full of mismatched socks when she came to visit.</p><a id="more"></a>  <p>In the days when my grandmothers were young women, the items of clothing in their wardrobe were considered valuable possessions that deserved looking after and mending to make their useful life last. One of the main differences between then and now seems to be the loss of our appetite for quality. We no longer buy with the intention for our clothes to last. When a jumper has a hole, we simply buy another one. </p><p>There doesn’t even have to be anything ‘wrong’ with the jumper per se. Being out of fashion tends to be a valid enough reason to allow it to be forgotten. To me, this all boils down to a lack of appreciation for the maker, for their craft and for our natural resources. </p><p>Luckily we are witnessing a growing social and environmental awareness that is making people more conscious of their clothes’ makers and materials. And this is where I see the ideal opportunity to reintroduce the skill of mending. I don’t mean to say that we all have to become experts at seamless repairing. In fact, I personally strongly subscribe to the Japanese tradition of kintsugi, which celebrates our items’ history by consciously making any mends visible.</p><p>These days, my husband, my children and I can be seen wearing crocheted elbow and knee patches like badges of honour. Out of love and respect for my two late grannies, I have found a way to marry both of their skills by carefully patching up holes using crochet squares and rectangles.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;My two late grandmothers were very skilful at making and mending clothes. My father’s mother was a natural at crocheting. Every summer, I still proudly wear one of her handmade cardigans. My mother’s mother was a meticulous sock darner and I remember her working her way through a basket full of mismatched socks when she came to visit.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="minimalism" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/minimalism/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Imperfectly Perfect</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2018/02/27/perfectly-imperfect/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2018/02/27/perfectly-imperfect/</id>
    <published>2018-02-27T15:00:20.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-02-28T09:46:56.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A week ago my relatives were on a train to us in London. The kids were eagerly anticipating their collection from the station. The fridge was waiting to be fed with wholesome food. I had put some vases by the sink to be filled with inviting blooms. My nose was considering a welcoming aroma for the oil burner. And I had booked a waltz with the vacuum cleaner.</p><a id="more"></a>  <p>Isn’t it remarkable how we can make even the most mundane tasks sound like poetry? In reality, any poetic sentiments I may have had towards my to-do-list, vanished as soon as I made one wrong move with the vacuum cleaner. My lower back seized up and I crashed to the floor in tears. The kids momentarily swapped excitement for concern but soon realised there was nothing they could do apart from quietly play around me. </p><p>Suffice it to say we never made it to the station. The fridge remained empty. As did the vases. And while I was contemplating my next move on the ‘dirty dance floor’, a blend of ylang ylang and sandal wood worked its very hardest to keep my emotions calm. Here I was lying with my own reality as the nimble yoga teacher scattered on the floor. I had imagined it all so perfectly perfect.</p><p>A couple of hours and a few testing moves later, the doorbell rang and was opened by the kids to a burst of absolute family joy. Suitcases landed straight from the London pavements on the carpet. The kettle was put on the hob to brew a pot of tea next to the empty vases. And before I knew it, dinner time had arrived and eight people were sitting around our very small kitchen table sharing a mezze of Indian takeaway dishes. The experience of this effortless comfort, despite the achy back, was so much better than I had dared to plan for. In the end it all turned out to be absolutely, imperfectly perfect.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;A week ago my relatives were on a train to us in London. The kids were eagerly anticipating their collection from the station. The fridge was waiting to be fed with wholesome food. I had put some vases by the sink to be filled with inviting blooms. My nose was considering a welcoming aroma for the oil burner. And I had booked a waltz with the vacuum cleaner.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="yoga" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/yoga/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>All Ears</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2017/11/16/allears/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2017/11/16/allears/</id>
    <published>2017-11-16T20:07:08.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-11-17T11:23:26.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been doing a little experiment lately: Every time one of the children chooses to confide in me, I do my utmost best to remain all ears. This simple mindfulness test has turned out to be more challenging than I had initially anticipated, yet also more rewarding.</p><a id="more"></a>  <p>The intention is to stay fully focused and concentrated, and to really listen to the message. This includes being aware of their facial expressions, body language, intonation, etc. It also means that I have to try and suspend my own judgement even if what I hear is something I disagree with or disapprove of.</p><p>Keeping my mind from wandering to what still ‘needs doing’, has been relatively easy within the context of this experiment. How long I can keep that up, remains to be seen. The hardest part, however, has been to steer clear of my own agenda. To truly listen, I have to let go of the need to interrupt, take control, provide advice, fix things, agree or disagree.</p><p>So, what are my findings after this very non-scientific bit of research, you may wonder? Well, the moments where I have actually managed to remain silent, focused and non-judgemental while they were confiding in me, have turned out to be rather magical. Realising that their story wasn’t going to be immediately squashed or frowned upon, they have truly opened up and revealed their feelings.</p><p>As a parent, it is hard not to claim ownership of our children’s emotions and to try and fix them. But rather than fixing things, shouldn’t we strive to provide a platform – even if occasionally a bit wobbly – where they feel safe to confide in us without fearing our condescending or condemning judgement?</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;I’ve been doing a little experiment lately: Every time one of the children chooses to confide in me, I do my utmost best to remain all ears. This simple mindfulness test has turned out to be more challenging than I had initially anticipated, yet also more rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="motherhood" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/motherhood/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
