<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Bubble + Sprout</title>
  
  <subtitle>A platform for positive expansion</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-04-28T20:30:40.860Z</updated>
  <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Karin Schrijvers</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Live Yoga Session with Karin</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2020/04/21/liveyogasession/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2020/04/21/liveyogasession/</id>
    <published>2020-04-21T21:20:18.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-04-28T20:30:40.860Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Please click on <a href="https://us04web.zoom.us/j/78142290047" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">Live Yoga Session with Karin</span></a> to access my live yoga session this Thursday from 10:30 - 11.00 UK time. See below for more information.</p><a id="more"></a><p>It is my intention to keep this first live session rather straightforward but it may still be a bit challenging for an absolute beginner. Feel free to sit out any pose that doesn’t suit you at the moment. This practice is for you to check in with your own breath and body. Remember that there is no need to compete with yourself or a family member on the mat next to you. If you do not have a yoga mat, make sure you have a cushion to sit on a floor that is not too     slippery.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Please click on &lt;a href=&quot;https://us04web.zoom.us/j/78142290047&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:grey&quot;&gt;Live Yoga Session with Karin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to access my live yoga session this Thursday from 10:30 - 11.00 UK time. See below for more information.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="yoga" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/yoga/"/>
    
    
      <category term="yoga" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/tags/yoga/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>King Coronavirus</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2020/04/16/kingcoronavirus/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2020/04/16/kingcoronavirus/</id>
    <published>2020-04-16T12:10:17.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-04-16T12:13:46.802Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Written by guest writer Tom Driscoll, aka my 7-year-old son</em></p><p>I wrote this letter to King Coronavirus because in school I had read Malala’s Magic Pencil by <a href="https://malala.org/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">Malala Yousafzai</span></a>. When Malala was a child, she wished for a magic pencil, so that if she drew or wrote something it would become the truth. She wished for a better life without war. I wish for the coronavirus to stop.</p><a id="more"></a><p>If I had a magic pencil, I would write a letter to King Coronavirus saying:</p><p>Dear King Coronavirus,</p><p>I don’t want to disappoint you, but please, pretty please can you stop making your army and your normal viruses invading the humans with their nasty diseases. Can you please stop doing this because there are 1,434,426 people who are tested. There have been 301,768 people who have recovered and 82,220 people who have died. I know that we are big opponents with Covid-19 city but we are dying. Even the English Prime Minister (Boris Johnson) is in hospital. I will give you whatever you want.</p><p>Yours sincerely,<br>Tom</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by guest writer Tom Driscoll, aka my 7-year-old son&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this letter to King Coronavirus because in school I had read Malala’s Magic Pencil by &lt;a href=&quot;https://malala.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:grey&quot;&gt;Malala Yousafzai&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. When Malala was a child, she wished for a magic pencil, so that if she drew or wrote something it would become the truth. She wished for a better life without war. I wish for the coronavirus to stop.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="motherhood" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/motherhood/"/>
    
    
      <category term="mindfulparenting" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/tags/mindfulparenting/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Plenty Enough</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2020/02/13/plentyenough/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2020/02/13/plentyenough/</id>
    <published>2020-02-13T20:25:37.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-04-16T12:08:10.263Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We listen to an audio book about tidying up while we shop for more. We book a yoga retreat away from everything and everyone on our way to meet with friends after work. We subscribe to a meditation app yet cannot find the time to use it.  </p><a id="more"></a><p>Rather than signing up for on-trend solutions that are marketed as the ultimate remedies for our busy lives, how about we learn to simply say “enough already”? On a daily basis, I introduce people to the virtues of yoga, meditation and a minimalist lifestyle. All three practices are incredibly powerful tools to help calm the chaos that can be everyday life. But have we as a people reached a stage where we no longer feel comfortable with calm in the first place? </p><p>I have been thinking about this a lot recently. Now that my kids are a little older and quite happy to entertain themselves after school, I struggle to fill the time gained with anything that I don’t consider ‘productive’. There I am, starting dinner much sooner than perhaps I should. Or occupying myself with one thing or another, just to stay busy. Sometimes I have to try hard to come up with something I could do to make myself feel busy. Or should I say to make myself feel useful? </p><p>I have become uncomfortable with downtime. Being busy keeps me from feeling unworthy. Who am I if not the busy mother, the consultant with a full schedule, the friend who is always available? The answer is, of course, very simple: I am enough and that is plenty.</p><p>Very often the practices that I work with are used as remedial tools. A lot of my clients are busy professionals, overwhelmed parents, and often both. Treating them to a yoga practice, guiding them through a meditation or helping them simplify an area in their home, does indeed bring calm. The beautiful essence of the practices, however, is that they can bring about a fundamental shift from the striving struggle of busy to the wholehearted embrace of enough. My new-found spare time has made me realise that I have been using my own practices to treat the symptoms of too much instead of tackle their cause. It’s time for me to shift back from not busy enough to plenty enough!</p><p><em>Image of The Asset Strippers by Mike Nelson at Tate Britain, 2019</em></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;We listen to an audio book about tidying up while we shop for more. We book a yoga retreat away from everything and everyone on our way to meet with friends after work. We subscribe to a meditation app yet cannot find the time to use it.  &lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="minimalism" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/minimalism/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Brain Boost</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/11/06/brainboost/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/11/06/brainboost/</id>
    <published>2019-11-06T15:18:01.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-11-07T12:02:26.796Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>In collaboration with <a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a></em></p><p>Mindful family sessions can offer clarity and calm amid the chaos that family life will inevitably bring. <a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE</span></a> and I have just completed an OM:POP series with <a href="https://www.family-support.org.uk/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">Family Support</span></a> in West London and can confirm that mindful practices deliver a sense of wellbeing even with a whole host of tiny tots in the room.</p><a id="more"></a><p>We have been working with Family Support to help children, young people and their families thrive by bringing weekly mindfulness sessions to West London families. Family yoga teacher extraordinaire, <a href="https://www.zenarmstrong.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">Jen Armstrong</span></a>, and I created a 7-week series based on the metaphors that Family Support use to expand people’s understanding of brain development.</p><p>Our OM:POP series covers the following of their brain metaphors:</p><ul><li><a href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/09/05/brainarchitecture/#nav-anchor"><span style="color:grey">Brain Architecture</span></a></li><li><a href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/09/28/pingpong/#nav-anchor"><span style="color:grey">Serve and Return</span></a></li><li><a href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/10/08/innercalm/#nav-anchor"><span style="color:grey">Toxic Stress</span></a></li><li><a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/blog/2019/10/8/ompop-brain-building-air-traffic-control" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">Executive Functioning</span></a></li><li><a href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/10/23/goodvibrations/#nav-anchor"><span style="color:grey">Resilience</span></a></li></ul><p>Each weekly session briefly touches upon the theory behind one of the metaphors and then introduces applicable yoga and meditation techniques that help build and strengthen the brain. During the last session we merge all our learnings and tools into a fully integrated yoga and meditation practice that embraces all of the covered metaphors. After a grounding and heart-opening family yoga practice, parents and caregivers are guided through a seated meditation to invite in a calm presence before their final send-off.</p><p>If you would like to experience for yourself how this practice can give you a comprehensive brain-building boost, feel free to take a comfortable seated position on a chair or cross-legged on the floor and try out the following shortened practice:</p><ul><li>With your hands on your thighs, inhale while you circle your upper body to the left and then front. Exhale and circle your upper body to the right and back again to your starting position. Move fluidly with your breath while you make a large clockwise circle with your chest and shoulders, moving from just above your hips. Both sitting bones stay grounded throughout the circular movement. Repeat 3 to 5 times</li><li>After your chosen number of clockwise circles, change direction. Again, draw 3 to 5 wide circles with your upper body to open the hips and strengthen the core. Finish the circular anti-clockwise movements in the upright starting position.</li><li>If you are sitting cross-legged, now bring the other leg in front. If you are seated on a chair, move a little to the front of the seat. Interlace your fingers and extend your arms and palms to the front while you exhale and round your spine. Your ears will end up in line with your upper arms. Inhale, lift up your arms and bring your spine upright. Exhale to separate your hands and circle the arms down your sides. With the next in-breath, interlace your fingers behind your tailbone. Draw the knuckles of the fingers down towards the floor and lift your breast bone. Repeat this wavelike spinal motion 3 to 5 times.</li><li>Now sit upright again. If you are seated on a chair, slide back until your back is supported by the back rest. Close your eyes. Lift your breastbone and very slightly drop the chin.</li><li>Palms face up and are resting on your thighs. Bring the tips of your index fingers to touch the tips of your thumbs and extend your three remaining fingers out to the front.</li><li>Breathe smoothly through the nostrils</li><li>The lips stay sealed</li><li>Observe your breath’s rhythm</li><li>Allow the breath to be complete yet stay natural</li><li>Tune in to your senses: listen, feel, smell, see (with eyes closed), taste (with mouth closed)</li><li>Observe your mental activities and feelings</li><li>Accept all and sit with them for a few cycles of breathing</li><li>Now, let’s introduce our mantra. When you breathe in, silently say I AM in your head. When you breathe out, silently say the word CALM in your head. Inhale with the words I AM and exhale with the word CALM. Keep up the rhythmic repetition of the mantra and the breath. Each leading the other. </li><li>With every inhalation bring presence into the physical body and mind. With each exhalation drop into a sense of calm. </li><li>Repeat the mantra as often as suits you.</li><li>When it suits you, stop repeating the mantra.</li><li>Sit with your body, your breath and your mind.</li><li>When you are ready to come out, gently drop your chin to your chest, softly open your eyes and lift your head. </li></ul><p>Once you have expanded your awareness back into the space where you are sitting, notice whether you are feeling a little more clarity and calm. Then remember that a mindful awareness practice, such as this body-breath-mind practice, can not only help us find inner calm amid outer chaos but also rewire our brain to boost our wellbeing!</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://hereforyouforthem.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:grey&quot;&gt;HERE for you for them&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mindful family sessions can offer clarity and calm amid the chaos that family life will inevitably bring. &lt;a href=&quot;https://hereforyouforthem.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:grey&quot;&gt;HERE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I have just completed an OM:POP series with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.family-support.org.uk/&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:grey&quot;&gt;Family Support&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in West London and can confirm that mindful practices deliver a sense of wellbeing even with a whole host of tiny tots in the room.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="yoga" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/yoga/"/>
    
    
      <category term="mindfulparenting" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/tags/mindfulparenting/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Good Vibration</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/10/23/goodvibrations/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/10/23/goodvibrations/</id>
    <published>2019-10-23T20:33:52.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-10-23T20:32:54.497Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>In collaboration with <a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a></em></p><p>Parenting comes with its fair share of worries, anxiety and, well, stress. So how come some parents seem to do a better job at ‘handling’ stress than others? Perhaps they are more stress resilient? Yogic breathing is a practice that can help us build stress resilience.</p><a id="more"></a><p>When we possess a good dose of stress resilience, there is a fluid flexibility between two of the systems in our autonomic nervous system. Every time a stressful situation presents itself, the  sympathetic nervous system will be activated and cause a fight, flight, freeze, faint or fawn response. This is our body’s natural way of protecting itself from stressors. Once a stressful situation has been resolved and/or processed, stress resilience will help reactivate the parasympathetic nervous system that will lower our heart rate and our blood pressure. If the parasympathetic nervous system doesn’t kick in, however, our stress response will stay switched on and can, in the long run, negatively affect our mental and physical wellbeing.</p><p>Our breath is the one function of our nervous system that we can consciously control. That’s why yogic breathing can have such a profound effect on our overall health. Most of us have already experienced that a conscious breath can impact both our body and mind. Now research has shown that yogic breathing can positively affect our mood, and can even reduce anxiety and depression.</p><p>One yogic breathing practice that will help release feelings of frustration, anxiety or anger is brahmari pranayama or bee breathing. The exhalation in this practice resembles the humming of a bee. The sound naturally lengthens the exhalation and its vibration has a calming effect on our nerves. Bee breathing or brahmari pranayama is a very simple yet very effective breathing practice in any stressful situation. How about you give it a go and see what this humble bumble bee practice can do for you?</p><ul><li><p>Sit or stand upright, relax shoulders and lift breast bone.</p></li><li><p>Take a few conscious breaths and close your eyes (or not if this doesn’t work in your situation).</p></li><li><p>Softly close the lips and breathe in through the nostrils.</p></li><li><p>Exhale through the nostrils while you make the sound of the letter M. It will sound just like a bee humming inside your head. Keep this sound going for as long as feels good and until you need to breathe in. Don’t force the length of your exhalation while humming.</p></li><li><p>Repeat this cycle of smooth inhalation and buzzing exhalation as often as suits you.</p></li><li><p>Finally, be quiet and sit or stand like this for a while. Drop your chin to your chest. Softly open your eyes and lift your head.</p></li></ul><p>Once you have expanded your awareness back into the space where you are sitting or standing, notice whether there is a shift in your breath and/or your mood. Then remember that a mindful awareness practice, such as this yogic humming bee breath, can calm your nerves and release feelings of frustration, anxiety and even anger. Revisit this fun humming practice any time you are worried about how you may react to your feelings. And if you happen to have a small child with you, nobody will even look at you strangely while you are make a humming bee sound!</p><p><em><a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a> bring yoga and mindfulness to families. We are currently working together with <a href="https://www.family-support.org.uk/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">Family Support Hammersmith &amp; Fulham</span></a> to introduce London families to mindful awareness practices in a series of weekly workshops.</em></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://hereforyouforthem.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:grey&quot;&gt;HERE for you for them&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parenting comes with its fair share of worries, anxiety and, well, stress. So how come some parents seem to do a better job at ‘handling’ stress than others? Perhaps they are more stress resilient? Yogic breathing is a practice that can help us build stress resilience.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="yoga" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/yoga/"/>
    
    
      <category term="mindfulparenting" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/tags/mindfulparenting/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Inner Calm</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/10/08/innercalm/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/10/08/innercalm/</id>
    <published>2019-10-08T16:12:04.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-10-09T13:26:49.117Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>In collaboration with <a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a></em></p><p>We all experience stress. And while some stress can actually be positive, too much stress can negatively impact both our mental and physical wellbeing. The good news is that mindful awareness practices, such as yoga and meditation, can help calm our body’s stress response. </p><a id="more"></a><p>Even very young children (from 0 to 5) can experience three different kinds of stress: positive stress, tolerable stress and toxic stress. Positive stress – such as meeting a new person – are challenges that will actually help development. Tolerable stress – such as a death in the family – are challenges that could affect development but that are buffered by supportive relationships. Toxic stress are ongoing, severe challenges – like extreme poverty and abuse – without the consistent support of positive relationships. In order to build a solid brain architecture, it is the role of parents, caregivers or any other responsible adults to help calm the child’s stress response and to model coping skills. Of course the only way we adults can actually do this, is when we ourselves have mastered the coping skills that are needed to calm our own stress response.</p><p>Stress is everywhere. As adults we may experience stress symptoms when our children don’t behave as we would like them to, when we have seemingly endless to-do lists, when trying to manage our money, or in challenging relationships. And although a little bit of stress every now and then won’t do us any harm, it’s the severe and ongoing ‘toxic’ stress that can have a negative impact on our health. Mindful awareness practices, such as yoga and meditation, can support us in clearing unwanted stress energies that we carry around with us.</p><p>With a regular meditation practice, we can build up a reserve of inner calm. The following body scan meditation will clear away stress that may reside in our body. Depending on your available time for this practice, you may choose to bring your focused attention to either fewer or more body parts while you scan your way up from toes to head. The choice is yours.</p><ul><li><p>Lie on your back with your arms to your sides, palms up<br>Make sure the body feels fully supported and comfortable<br>Close your eyes</p></li><li><p>Inhale through the nostrils<br>Exhale through the mouth with an audible sigh<br>Repeat the same breath focus, relaxing your body when you exhale<br>Repeat the same breath focus again, giving in to the support of the floor when you exhale </p></li><li><p>Now breathe in through the nostrils and breathe out through the nostrils<br>The lips are softly sealed</p></li><li><p>Breathe into your toes and feet<br>Scoop up any unwelcome energy in the feet<br>Exhale and breathe it out</p></li><li><p>Breathe into the lower legs, calves and shins<br>Scoop up any unwanted energy in the lower legs<br>Exhale and let it go</p></li><li><p>Work your way up your body step by step, bringing your focused attention to the following body parts: knees, thighs, pelvis, abdomen, lower back, ribcage, heart centre, shoulders, upper arms, elbows, lower arms, wrists, hands, neck, face, brain centre<br>Each time you inhale, you look around for any unwanted energy<br>Each time you exhale, you breathe that energy out of the body part you are focusing on</p></li><li><p>Once you have scanned through the whole body, notice what it feels like to consciously relax your whole body from feet to head<br>Stay alert and present, smiling ever so slightly</p></li><li><p>When you feel ready to come out, slowly bring the your attention back to your breath<br>Introduce some movement into the body, perhaps beginning with fingers and toes<br>Draw up one knee at a time and roll to your right side<br>Stay there for a few breaths<br>Softly open the eyes<br>Push yourself up with head coming up last<br>Take a deep breath<br>Settle in and let the breath go</p></li><li><p>Drop your chin to your chest<br>Softly open your eyes and lift your head</p></li></ul><p>Once you have expanded your awareness back into the space where you are sitting, notice the clarity in your body and the calm in your mind.  Then remember that a mindful awareness practice, such as the body scan that you have just completed, can create a pool of calm for us to dip into as and when the need arises.</p><p><em><a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a> bring yoga and mindfulness to families. We are currently working together with <a href="https://www.family-support.org.uk/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">Family Support Hammersmith &amp; Fulham</span></a> to introduce London families to mindful awareness practices in a series of weekly workshops.</em></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://hereforyouforthem.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:grey&quot;&gt;HERE for you for them&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all experience stress. And while some stress can actually be positive, too much stress can negatively impact both our mental and physical wellbeing. The good news is that mindful awareness practices, such as yoga and meditation, can help calm our body’s stress response. &lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="yoga" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/yoga/"/>
    
    
      <category term="mindfulparenting" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/tags/mindfulparenting/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ping Pong</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/09/28/pingpong/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/09/28/pingpong/</id>
    <published>2019-09-28T14:59:55.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-09-29T10:14:16.021Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>In collaboration with <a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a></em></p><p>Ping and Pong. Send and Receive. Serve and Return. All word pairs that express the beautiful balance between giving and taking.</p><a id="more"></a><p>Being responsive to a young child’s babbles, cries, gestures and needs through eye contact, touch or words, is essential for the development of the child’s social and communication skills. These Serve &amp; Return interactions help strengthen the child’s <a href="https://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/09/05/brainarchitecture/#nav-anchor"><span style="color:grey">brain architecture</span></a>.</p><p>A parent or caregiver of small children will usually find it quite easy to bounce back the ball to the child. But are we in a ready position to receive? Let’s stop calling this bouncing thing a ball, and name it acceptance, recognition and love. It comes quite naturally to give these sentiments to our child or children. Feeding our own hearts and minds with them can be a little more challenging. Yet, how can we keep giving when the wellspring that is our heart feels depleted?</p><p>Cultivating self-love is a practice that takes patience and acceptance of our own vulnerability. The following brief meditation provides a platform to welcome in acceptance, recognition and love for our most vulnerable self. When we nourish the source, it will rebound with an abundance to give.</p><ul><li><p>Sit in a comfortable position<br>Close your eyes<br>Rest your hands on your thighs, palms up<br>Touch thumb to index finger<br>Breathe deeply</p></li><li><p>Inhale to welcome in a connection to your heart<br>Exhale to connect with the hearts outside the confinement of your physical body</p></li><li><p>Your focused attention to the heart will bring it a sensation of warmth </p></li><li><p>Breathe in to receive acceptance in your heart centre<br>Breathe out to spread acceptance from your heart centre</p></li><li><p>Breathe in to receive recognition in your heart centre<br>Breathe out to spread recognition from your heart centre</p></li><li><p>Breathe in to receive love in your heart centre<br>Breathe out to spread love from your heart centre</p></li><li><p>Notice a longer exhalation. More giving and sharing.<br>Notice a longer inhalation. More to take in and give your self.</p></li><li><p>Honour where you are at this very moment<br>Let yourself be nourished by the practice of both giving and receiving</p></li><li><p>Continue to breathe in the warmth that you are receiving<br>Continue to breathe out the warmth that originates in your heart centre</p></li><li><p>Take a few more conscious, deep breaths with this heart focused attention</p></li><li><p>Drop your chin to your chest<br>Softly open your eyes and lift your head</p></li></ul><p>Once you have expanded your awareness back into the space where you are sitting, notice whether you feel recharged and ready to keep ponging back each ping. Then remember that with a patient and accepting practice we can be our own brain architect as well as our children’s.</p><p><em><a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a> bring yoga and mindfulness to families. We are currently working together with <a href="https://www.family-support.org.uk/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">Family Support Hammersmith &amp; Fulham</span></a> to introduce London families to mindful awareness practices in a series of weekly workshops.</em></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://hereforyouforthem.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:grey&quot;&gt;HERE for you for them&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ping and Pong. Send and Receive. Serve and Return. All word pairs that express the beautiful balance between giving and taking.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="motherhood" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/motherhood/"/>
    
    
      <category term="mindfulparenting" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/tags/mindfulparenting/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Brain Architect</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/09/05/brainarchitecture/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/09/05/brainarchitecture/</id>
    <published>2019-09-05T15:13:49.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-09-05T18:06:07.384Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>In collaboration with <a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a></em></p><p>Our kids’ earliest experiences play an essential part in the construction of their brain architecture. It is at this stage that the foundation for lifelong physical and mental health is laid down. But what about the architecture of the parents’ brains? Can we still make structural changes or do some rewiring for our own wellbeing?</p><a id="more"></a><p>Fortunately, the belief that an old dog cannot be taught new tricks has officially been disproven by a mounting number of neuroscientific studies. There is more and more evidence to confirm that our brain does not lose its plasticity as we get older. And luckily for us, the saying that practice makes perfect has not been buried with that old dog. Although I would prefer it as “practice makes better” (or even awesome, as <a href="https://matthewsyed.co.uk/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">Matthew Syed</span></a>  would have it).</p><p>Brain research has shown that a focused practice can bring about structural changes that improve the communication between the different parts of our extended nervous system. In other words, with consistent and focused practice, our brain architecture is sufficiently adaptable for us to rewire and bring about structural changes throughout our entire life. That is pretty cool.</p><p>And here is an even cooler thing for us parents. A focused practice can rewire our brain connections to such an extend that it can help move us from a state of chaos to a state of calm. Let’s sit with that for a breath or two or more…</p><p>Well done. You have now officially taken the first step on your journey to rewire your brain for optimal integration. Conscious breathing together with mindful movement and paying attention to the mind, are the three key aspects of a mindful awareness practice that will help improve the wiring of your extended nervous system and bring about harmony.</p><p>Why not allow yourself a brief moment to try out the following focused practice? Start with a few minutes only and see for yourself whether it can really bring about a harmonious sense of calm for you:</p><ul><li>Start with some fluid, mindful movements. These could be done standing, on hands and knees, or sitting down on a chair or floor. Let your body lead the way through gentle joint and spinal movements. They could be as simple as turning your head from side to side, circling your arms, arching and rounding your back. Once you feel that you have awakened your physical body, sit in a comfortable and supported upright position.</li><li>Connect with your breath. Close your eyes and observe the breath’s rhythm. Notice how the breath automatically deepens and lengthens when you give it your attention. Perhaps count the length of each breath, and note how it gradually increases. Aim for a complete yet natural breath.</li><li>Now bring your mind’s attention to what you can sense around you. Turn down your gaze with your eyes closed. Register the sounds around you. Feel the air on your skin. Allow the sweet taste of that last cup of tea to linger. Smell the coffee that is brewing in the kitchen. Tune in to your senses, your bodily sensations, your connection with others and your mental activities. Now simply sit with this. Sit with your body, with your breath, with your sensations and with your feelings. Avoid judging what you experience. Simply notice and accept. </li><li>After a short while, begin to expand your attention from your mind back to your body and beyond. Take a deep breath. Open your eyes. Move slowly.</li></ul><p>Once you have expanded your awareness outwards and returned to daily life, notice whether you can respond more calmly to any chaotic demands. Even if just on one small occasion. And then remember that with a consistent and focused practice we can be our own brain architect and rewire for this transition from chaos to calm to become second nature.</p><p><em><a href="https://hereforyouforthem.com/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">HERE for you for them</span></a> bring yoga and mindfulness to families. We are currently working together with <a href="https://www.family-support.org.uk/" target="_blank" rel="external"><span style="color:grey">Family Support Hammersmith &amp; Fulham</span></a> to introduce London families to mindful awareness practices in a series of weekly workshops.</em></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://hereforyouforthem.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:grey&quot;&gt;HERE for you for them&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our kids’ earliest experiences play an essential part in the construction of their brain architecture. It is at this stage that the foundation for lifelong physical and mental health is laid down. But what about the architecture of the parents’ brains? Can we still make structural changes or do some rewiring for our own wellbeing?&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="motherhood" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/motherhood/"/>
    
    
      <category term="mindfulparenting" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/tags/mindfulparenting/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Anger Modelling</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/07/01/mindfulmodel/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/07/01/mindfulmodel/</id>
    <published>2019-07-01T12:58:21.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-07-01T16:59:39.776Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s what our daughter shared with me during our little chat the other day: But mama, you NEVER get angry! </p><a id="more"></a><p>Initially, I felt a surge of pride. How cool is that? My kids don’t think I get angry. Or at least one of them does. It didn’t take me long to realise, however, that this is not a good thing, and far from the truth of course. The problem is that from experiences at school or elsewhere, she has come to associate feeling angry with an ‘aggressive’ reaction. There I was thinking that she understood I was angry whenever I took a deep breath or walked out of the room. But how could she? In my wholehearted attempt at modelling mindfulness, I had never once named my emotion of anger before I tamed it.</p><p>The reason for our chat was an unusually powerful outburst after she had struggled to find a kind response towards her little brother. To be honest, he does have a habit of seeing how far he can push her. And until recently, she seems to have had a very deep well of tolerance. Unfortunately for him, turns out the well is not bottomless. Let’s just say, as Daniel J. Siegel, M.D. and Tina Payne Bryson, PH.D. would so eloquently have it in their must-read “No-Drama Discipline”, that she ended up ‘flipping her lid’.</p><p>A few minutes later, after I had gathered the courage to open her firmly shut bedroom door, we were lying on the bed and it felt like the right time to have a talk. It was then that she expressed that she had no practical tools to stop herself from ‘losing it’ and that this worried her. I tried to remind her how when I am angry, I take a pause or a deep breath or even walk out of the room. Funnily enough, she had no idea that I even get angry or do any of these things… Some mindful model I must have been?</p><p>I came to realise that although I have seemingly been rather good at providing non-reactive responses, I have been absolutely useless at expressing my emotions when it comes down to anger. With the acknowledgment of our feelings being a key aspect of the practice of mindfulness, I fear that in that sense I have let the kids down by not being explicit enough about my emotions. Don’t get me wrong, I don’t think I am too bad at expressing joy and surprise, or sadness, fear and even disgust. But somehow, as my daughter clearly pointed out, I have been covering up the emotion of anger by trying too hard to model a mindful response.</p><p>Once I had understood and processed the above, my daughter and I ended up writing down the following list of strategies that we can use when we feel ourselves getting angry:</p><ul><li>Count to 10 in our head</li><li>Clench and unclench our fists</li><li>Close our eyes</li><li>Take a few deep and slow breaths</li><li>Leave the room</li><li>Talk to someone else</li></ul><p>So next time one of the kids or a situation is getting on my nerves, I will do my level best to clearly express that I am feeling angry before I apply one of our strategies. This will definitely require diligence and patience, but it will hopefully end up teaching all of us that emotions need to be acknowledged before we find an appropriate way to respond to them.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Here’s what our daughter shared with me during our little chat the other day: But mama, you NEVER get angry! &lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="motherhood" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/motherhood/"/>
    
    
      <category term="mindfulparenting" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/tags/mindfulparenting/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Meal Rhythm</title>
    <link href="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/05/14/mealrhythm/"/>
    <id>http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/2019/05/14/mealrhythm/</id>
    <published>2019-05-14T13:41:42.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-05-14T13:14:23.706Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months ago it became very clear that our kids have reached a picky eater stage. Especially our 8 year old. Although I am preparing myself for the same to happen with our 6 year old a few years from now. </p><a id="more"></a><p>Short of causing an identity crisis, this new development rather baffled me. Here I was, the mother who had been somewhat proud (some may even dare call it slightly smug) about the fact that her kids always were the ones who ate or at least tried everything that they were served. Not so much any more. At least not within the walls of our home.</p><p>When the kids walk in the door from school, both love to express the intensity of their hunger in the most fanciful and exaggerated adjectives. On a daily basis we are exposed to such terms as ravenous, famished and starving. All quite hopeful for the one who is cooking the evening meal.<br>So when ringing our rather pavlovian little bell to announce dinnertime, we always had great expectations of gratitude and empty plates. Let’s just say that it only took a few turned up noses and extremely vocal complaints for us to realise that this family needed to revise its meal planning.</p><p>This is when the four of us sat down together and agreed to develop a meal rhythm. We quickly landed on the following rhythmic approach to dinnertime: </p><p>Monday – Potato dish<br>Tuesday – Homemade pizza<br>Wednesday – Egg dish<br>Thursday – Smorgasbord<br>Friday – Quesadillas<br>Saturday – Steak and chips<br>Sunday – Anything goes</p><p>You may think that apart from Sundays, we are eating exactly the same thing every day of the week, but you would be surprised to find out how much you can do with a humble potato! The meals also remain varied because of the unpredictable content of our weekly organic fruit and veg delivery, which allows us to continue to expose the kids to different types of food. Pizza provides a platform for an endless array of toppings, for example. </p><p>The kids know what to expect. Even if this means a couple of fried eggs on a black bean and salsa burrito for their Wednesday meal. They still may not like it, but they are much more likely to give it a go. And for us, the makers of the meal, this new arrangement has also brought a totally new dimension to the week. No more running out of ideas yet still an opportunity to be creative where we see fit. The main rhythm is set, the only thing left to do is to adapt the melody to the mood of the moment.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;A few months ago it became very clear that our kids have reached a picky eater stage. Especially our 8 year old. Although I am preparing myself for the same to happen with our 6 year old a few years from now. &lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="minimalism" scheme="http://www.bubbleandsprout.com/categories/minimalism/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
